<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-19T10:59:33-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Article in Journal of French Language Studies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022-07-19-article-in-Journal-of-French-Language-Studies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Article in Journal of French Language Studies" /><published>2022-07-19T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-07-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article-in-Journal-of-French-Language-Studies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022-07-19-article-in-Journal-of-French-Language-Studies.html">&lt;p&gt;My article “Reflections of the French nasal vowel shift in orthography on Twitter” has just been published in a special issue of the &lt;em&gt;Journal of French Language Studies&lt;/em&gt;. The special issue covers French variation in digital media, with articles discussing the special forms that French takes in text messages, chat, and social media. My article discusses the spelling of nasal vowels on Twitter. Depending on the variety of French, there are usually 3 or 4 different nasal vowels. Because the way these vowels are pronounced has shifted over time, their traditional spelling doesn’t always straightforwardly reflect their pronunciation. For example, in a word like &lt;em&gt;avant&lt;/em&gt; ‘before’, the second &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; differs from the first not only in its nasal quality, but also in its place of articulation, which is closer to an oral &lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt; [ɔ̃]. On Twitter, where some people can be pretty playful in their spelling, I observed spellings like &lt;em&gt;avont&lt;/em&gt; that reflect this shifted pronunciation. In my study, I compared the frequency of shifted spellings of different words to see whether words that tend to show more shifted pronunciation in speech are also more likely to have these shifted spellings. This turns out not to be the case, and I suspect it’s because the factors that affect shifted pronunciation in speech (things like prosodic stress and phonological context) can conflict with the factors that affect creative spellings (things like written word length and spell-check). Still, the fact that these spellings are observed on Twitter (often with special markers like capitalizing the changed letter) shows that speakers are aware of this sound change and use spelling to comment on it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">My article “Reflections of the French nasal vowel shift in orthography on Twitter” has just been published in a special issue of the Journal of French Language Studies. The special issue covers French variation in digital media, with articles discussing the special forms that French takes in text messages, chat, and social media. My article discusses the spelling of nasal vowels on Twitter. Depending on the variety of French, there are usually 3 or 4 different nasal vowels. Because the way these vowels are pronounced has shifted over time, their traditional spelling doesn’t always straightforwardly reflect their pronunciation. For example, in a word like avant ‘before’, the second a differs from the first not only in its nasal quality, but also in its place of articulation, which is closer to an oral o [ɔ̃]. On Twitter, where some people can be pretty playful in their spelling, I observed spellings like avont that reflect this shifted pronunciation. In my study, I compared the frequency of shifted spellings of different words to see whether words that tend to show more shifted pronunciation in speech are also more likely to have these shifted spellings. This turns out not to be the case, and I suspect it’s because the factors that affect shifted pronunciation in speech (things like prosodic stress and phonological context) can conflict with the factors that affect creative spellings (things like written word length and spell-check). Still, the fact that these spellings are observed on Twitter (often with special markers like capitalizing the changed letter) shows that speakers are aware of this sound change and use spelling to comment on it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">French Grammar textbook published</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022-07-01-French-Grammar-textbook-published.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="French Grammar textbook published" /><published>2022-07-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-07-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/French-Grammar-textbook-published</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022-07-01-French-Grammar-textbook-published.html">&lt;p&gt;The course I teach most often is Advanced French Part 1 (French 321). This is an important course in my department, because it is usually the first course taken by new students who learned French as missionaries. For many of those who go on to major or minor in French in my department, French 321 is where they first started considering their course of study. I work hard to improve this course every semester to make a good first impression with these students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way I’ve been wanting to improve the course is with an updated textbook. The textbook that has traditionally been used in this course (and the Part 2 course that follows it) has been receiving declining support from its publisher, and like many college textbooks suffers from problems of expense and outdated information. In my graduate studies at the University of Texas, I did some work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coerll.utexas.edu/coerll/&quot;&gt;COERLL&lt;/a&gt;, the Center for Open Educational Resources and Language Learning. COERLL is funded by the Department of Education and housed at UT Austin with the mission to create foreign language education resources and publish them under an open license — i.e., for free and with open rights for educators to remix the materials as they see fit. Open educational resources (OERs) are the future of education, and I saw the development of an OER textbook as a top priority for French 321. With an OER textbook, I’m able to update the material regularly to keep it current (such as to describe changes in how French is used online, or the neopronouns used by some nonbinary French speakers, or new findings regarding understudied varieties of French in Africa, North America, and the Pacific). Other teachers are able to publish their own modified versions of an OER textbook to suit their own courses. And most importantly, students (and anyone else on the internet who wants to improve their French) can access the textbook for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So since late last year, I’ve been working on a new textbook for advanced French grammar, &lt;em&gt;Grammaire Ouverte&lt;/em&gt;. I started with an existing OER, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.laits.utexas.edu/tex/&quot;&gt;Tex’s French Grammar&lt;/a&gt; (published by COERLL), which is intended for beginning students and written in English. To make it appropriate for French 321, I organized it into thematic chapters, translated it into French, wrote new sections to add more detail on advanced topics, and did a lot of revising. I also added some features to make this textbook a better learning tool: chapter intros based around excerpts from public domain French novels, a glossary of French linguistic terms, examples from a large and diversified linguistic corpus (the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shs-conferences.org/articles/shsconf/abs/2016/05/shsconf_cmlf2016_11002/shsconf_cmlf2016_11002.html&quot;&gt;CRFC&lt;/a&gt;, which Dirk Siepmann from Osnabrück University was kind enough to share access to), notes on dialectal and stylistic variation (with lots of insights gained from my reading of the newly published and wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.xn--grandegrammairedufranais-gec.com/&quot;&gt;Grande Grammaire du Français&lt;/a&gt;), and quizzes at the end of each chapter. The book is published through BYU’s OER platform at &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.byu.edu/grammaire_ouverte&quot;&gt;open.byu.edu/grammaire_ouverte&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been really pleased with the experience. BYU’s OER platform is really easy to use, and while writing I’ve learned a ton about both French grammar and web design. Although my attention will shift back toward my research now, this project has gotten me excited to develop more OER’s for my other courses in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">The course I teach most often is Advanced French Part 1 (French 321). This is an important course in my department, because it is usually the first course taken by new students who learned French as missionaries. For many of those who go on to major or minor in French in my department, French 321 is where they first started considering their course of study. I work hard to improve this course every semester to make a good first impression with these students.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Article in Cognitive Linguistics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022-04-25-article-in-Cognitive-Linguistics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Article in Cognitive Linguistics" /><published>2022-04-25T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-04-25T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article-in-Cognitive-Linguistics%20-%20Copy%20-%20Copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022-04-25-article-in-Cognitive-Linguistics.html">&lt;p&gt;My article “Metonymy and argument alternations in French communication frames” has just been published in the journal &lt;em&gt;Cognitive Linguistics&lt;/em&gt;. This article expands on work from my dissertation. I investigated French words that express communication, particularly those dealing with revealing a secret (i.e. &lt;em&gt;révéler&lt;/em&gt; ‘reveal’, &lt;em&gt;divulguer&lt;/em&gt; ‘divulge’, &lt;em&gt;dévoilement&lt;/em&gt; ‘unveiling’, etc.). Around these words, the semantic arguments can alternate — for example, you can say that a Speaker revealed a secret (&lt;em&gt;Jean révèle…&lt;/em&gt;) or that a Medium of communication revealed a secret (&lt;em&gt;Le livre révèle…&lt;/em&gt;). These alternations are examples of metonymy, a mental mechanism that allows linked concepts to stand for one another. I looked at alternations like this historically, finding that certain alternations became more frequent in written French over the past few centuries. The analysis shows connections between sociohistorical changes (such as the rise of print media in Europe) and lexico-constructional changes in the language. You can read the full article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www-degruyter-com.erl.lib.byu.edu/document/doi/10.1515/cog-2021-0072/html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">My article “Metonymy and argument alternations in French communication frames” has just been published in the journal Cognitive Linguistics. This article expands on work from my dissertation. I investigated French words that express communication, particularly those dealing with revealing a secret (i.e. révéler ‘reveal’, divulguer ‘divulge’, dévoilement ‘unveiling’, etc.). Around these words, the semantic arguments can alternate — for example, you can say that a Speaker revealed a secret (Jean révèle…) or that a Medium of communication revealed a secret (Le livre révèle…). These alternations are examples of metonymy, a mental mechanism that allows linked concepts to stand for one another. I looked at alternations like this historically, finding that certain alternations became more frequent in written French over the past few centuries. The analysis shows connections between sociohistorical changes (such as the rise of print media in Europe) and lexico-constructional changes in the language. You can read the full article here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Article in edited volume</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022-03-27-article-in-edited-volume.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Article in edited volume" /><published>2022-03-27T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-03-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article-in-edited-volume</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022-03-27-article-in-edited-volume.html">&lt;p&gt;The volume &lt;em&gt;Directions for Pedagogical Construction Grammar: Learning and Teaching (with) Constructions&lt;/em&gt; edited by Hans Boas has just been published. The book includes my article “Frame-based metonymy in teaching L2 vocabulary”. In this article, I provide a practical example of adapting a traditional approach to teaching verbs (based around inflectional sets) to a construction-based approach organized around semantic frames. Along the way, I discuss how teaching in this way can help students to integrate figurative devices such as metonymy, which is ubiquitous in natural language, into their L2 production. This work represents a first step towards practical application of my research on metonymy in semantic frames, which I’ve explored in my dissertation and elsewhere. You can check out the full volume over on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/books/edition/Directions_for_Pedagogical_Construction/SOxcEAAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&quot;&gt;Google Books&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Directions-Pedagogical-Construction-Grammar-Constructions/dp/3110746646/ref=sr_1_1?crid=36FDSPUPBCPOE&amp;amp;keywords=Directions+for+Pedagogical+Construction+Grammar+Learning+and+Teaching+%28with%29+Constructions&amp;amp;qid=1652460994&amp;amp;sprefix=directions+for+pedagogical+construction+grammar+learning+and+teaching+with+constructions%2Caps%2C135&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">The volume Directions for Pedagogical Construction Grammar: Learning and Teaching (with) Constructions edited by Hans Boas has just been published. The book includes my article “Frame-based metonymy in teaching L2 vocabulary”. In this article, I provide a practical example of adapting a traditional approach to teaching verbs (based around inflectional sets) to a construction-based approach organized around semantic frames. Along the way, I discuss how teaching in this way can help students to integrate figurative devices such as metonymy, which is ubiquitous in natural language, into their L2 production. This work represents a first step towards practical application of my research on metonymy in semantic frames, which I’ve explored in my dissertation and elsewhere. You can check out the full volume over on Google Books or Amazon.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Presenting at GRATO</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021-11-16-presenting-at-GRATO.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Presenting at GRATO" /><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/presenting-at-GRATO</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021-11-16-presenting-at-GRATO.html">&lt;p&gt;This weekend I am presenting at the online conference &lt;a href=&quot;https://clunl.fcsh.unl.pt/en/eventos-cientificos/grato/grato-2021/&quot;&gt;7th International Conference on Grammar and Text&lt;/a&gt;. The conference is hosted in Lisbon, although I will unfortunately only be presenting online. The title of my talk is “Text genre and participant role alternations in the French Spending frame.” I will be discussing the important role that genre plays in affecting the use of participant role alternations in some of the data from my dissertation. You can view my slides here: &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/downloads/GRATO2021_Law.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;download slides&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">This weekend I am presenting at the online conference 7th International Conference on Grammar and Text. The conference is hosted in Lisbon, although I will unfortunately only be presenting online. The title of my talk is “Text genre and participant role alternations in the French Spending frame.” I will be discussing the important role that genre plays in affecting the use of participant role alternations in some of the data from my dissertation. You can view my slides here: link.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Presenting at LxGr</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021-07-01-presenting-at-LxGr.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Presenting at LxGr" /><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-07-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/presenting-at-LxGr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021-07-01-presenting-at-LxGr.html">&lt;p&gt;This weekend I am presenting at the online conference &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edgehill.ac.uk/englishhistorycreativewriting/research/lxgr/?tab=lxgr-archive&quot;&gt;Corpus Approaches to LexicoGrammar&lt;/a&gt;. The title of my talk is “A lexicogrammatical approach to participant role alternations in the French Spending frame.” I will be drawing from data collected for my dissertation to discuss the interface between syntax and the lexicon. You can view my slides here: &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/downloads/LxGr2021_Law.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;download slides&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">This weekend I am presenting at the online conference Corpus Approaches to LexicoGrammar. The title of my talk is “A lexicogrammatical approach to participant role alternations in the French Spending frame.” I will be drawing from data collected for my dissertation to discuss the interface between syntax and the lexicon. You can view my slides here: link.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Starting at BYU</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020-08-20-starting-at-byu.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting at BYU" /><published>2020-08-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/starting-at-byu</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020-08-20-starting-at-byu.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m about to start my first year teaching at BYU! It has been an odd year — the COVID-19 pandemic hit the US right before I defended my dissertation. I ended up defending in my slippers at home in Alabama, miles away from my committee at the University of Texas. Now I’m in Provo figuring out how I’m going to teach when half my students are masked and socially distanced in the classroom and the other half are watching from home. Still, I’m so grateful to be back at my alma mater, teaching the subjects I love!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">I’m about to start my first year teaching at BYU! It has been an odd year — the COVID-19 pandemic hit the US right before I defended my dissertation. I ended up defending in my slippers at home in Alabama, miles away from my committee at the University of Texas. Now I’m in Provo figuring out how I’m going to teach when half my students are masked and socially distanced in the classroom and the other half are watching from home. Still, I’m so grateful to be back at my alma mater, teaching the subjects I love!</summary></entry></feed>